#### ANDROID DEVELOPER

### Career Overview

Over 5 years of Software Industry Experience in analysis design, development, testing, debugging and deploying of web, java and mobile applications. 3 years' experience in Java application development. 2 years' experience in Android mobile application development. Experience in Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC), Object Oriented analysis design. Eclipse IDE, Plug in ADT, Android SDK, JAVA, XML, SQLite, Linux, DDMS, Trace Viewer, debugging tools JSON, HTML, and HTML5. Experience in development of Object Oriented programming applications using Java technologies. Experience in Android application UI design implementation and development. Experience of Web services in android and efficient data transfer between servers and devices. Experience in Android activities, cool home widgets, services, Broadcast receivers, Content providers, fragments, intent, intent filters, supporting multiple screens and configurations. Experience of common android framework, framework APIs (Location, Camera, Notifications, Maps), and Google APIs (Location Manager). Experience in Multi-threading and background tasks. Experience in Optimizing for multiple device screen sizes and OS versions. Excellent with Java OOP, Core Java, Inheritance, Abstraction, Encapsulation, and Polymorphism Excellent skills in troubleshooting, debugging, and testing Android applications using various version control systems.

## Work Experience

Android Developer 09/2013 to Current Apex Systems Beale Air Force Base, CA

- The Coca-Cola Freestyle app helps users find the nearest spot where they can explore endless possibilities.
- With its location finder, users can discover nearby locations that have a Coca-Cola Freestyle fountain with 100+ choices waiting for them.
- It also shows them where to get good deals from their favorite restaurants, movie theaters and more.
- Once they find a place to enjoy, they can earn badges and prizes by checking in and exploring all of the brands available.
- They can also use the app to explore and save their favorite brands.
- Responsibilities: Worked with the Android SDK, and implemented Android Bluetooth and Location Connectivity components.
- Used SQLite to cache the data received from the RESTful web services.
- Constructing HTTP requests, fetching server response and parsing feeds wherever required.
- Analysis of mobile application code for re-engineering.
- Involved in requirement gathering and designing of the application.
- Responsible for consuming the REST services, getting JSON response and parsing them to get the required information.
- Implemented Google Maps API v2 with forward and reverse geo-location.
- Integrated location based services using Google Maps API to display locations of the nearest stores.
- Implemented unique design for portrait and landscape mode.
- Handling XML data using efficient parsing techniques such as DOM parser.
- Used GIT-HUB as our project version controller, where used to commit and push the developed, working code Work closely with the web
  application development team to ensure proper integration between mobile application and web application.
- Tested the application on various Android devices.
- Used Crashlytics, while testing the application, so as to verify the proper free-flow working of the application Environment: Android SDK 4.4, Eclipse IDE, JSON, REST Web Services, XML, Crashlytics, Trello-board, Action-Bar and GIT-HUB.

#### Android Developer 11/2012 to 08/2013 Apex Systems Bear River City, UT

- Dow Snowglobe is an interactive snow globe.
- We can choose from different scene backgrounds and choose your own picture to resize and fit inside of the globe.
- Application allows you to shake or use your finger to swirl the snow around.
- Responsibilities: As a team member, I was involved in the design and implementation of the UI, classes, architecture and activities of the mobile application Used Frame Layout method to show background images of the app.
- Involved in implementing AsyncTask for the background operations.
- Developed the app to adapt to different orientations (Landscape/Portrait) and various resolutions (ldpi/mdpi/hdpi) based on the device Implemented MotionEvent method to swirl the snow around with a shake.
- Implemented TouchEvent method to swirl the snow around with the use of finger Developed analytics for the application so as to keep a track of the app on which device and in which places it has been used.
- Designed and developed the request and response data to and from gallery.
- Participated in all the phases of SDLC from design, development through testing, porting and support of application.
- Environment: SDK 4.4, Eclipse IDE, FrameLayouts, DDMS console and User Interface Design.

## Android Developer 08/2011 to 11/2012 Apex Systems Bedford, MA

- Motorola Help lets you view FAQs, tutorials and tips about your device.
- Also, you can get direct access to Motorola Customer Care when you need more assistance with your phone.
- Responsibilities: Designed screens related to categories and detail pages for this application.
- Developed quick search functionalities in this application.
- Involved in requirement gathering and designing of the application.
- Responsible for consuming the REST services, getting a JSON response and parsing them to get the required information.
- Implemented the Dashboard, Action Bar, Quick action UI Design Pattern and Draw-9 Patch Images.
- Worked on local data storage using SQLite.
- Worked on the Android AsyncTask service to update List View Screen.
- Implemented the Android animation style & gesture events to flip the Screen/Layout.
- Implemented in Android App for persisting java objects to SQLite Database.

- Involved in developer testing by porting the app on multiple devices with various screen sizes.
- Worked with design/UX team to create user-friendly, aesthetically pleasing, and full functional UI.
- Followed the agile methodology for implementing the project.
- Had to closely work with QA team while fixing bugs.

# Java/J2EE Developer $07/2010\ to\ 08/2011$ Synechron Inc Minneapolis , MN

- This project is to create an application for Time Warner Cable internal user and wholesale users to facilitate the process.
- The application will capture the request from any end customer for new landline or internet connection.
- The request has to go through various steps like account creation, user's personal detail collection, serviceability check in the requested area, servicing the request etc.
- Responsibilities: The database connectivity was done using JDBC to connect to the MS SQL Server database in the backend.
- Developed user interface using JSF, JSP, Java Script and HTML.
- Created application to connect to database by using JDBC, connection pools, callable statements and prepared statements.
- Designed and Developed Web services using technologies UDDI, WSDL, SOAP, REST to communicate to the other modules.
- Implemented web-service integration components from SOA using SOAP, WSDL and RESTful webservices.
- Developed Action classes for Struts framework and implemented Java classes for the corresponding Struts Actions.
- Used XML, WSDL, UDDI, SOAP, SAX parser and Web services for communicating data between different application Design and developed web based Configuration tool Used JNDI and data source for database connection.
- Used Log4J logging framework to write log messages with various levels.
- Involved in fixing bugs and minor enhancements for the front-end modules.
- Used VSS for version control.
- Used Maven to build the application.
- Used Eclipse IDE for the development environment.
- Deployed the application on JBoss Application Server.

# JAVA/J2EE Developer 05/2009 to 07/2010 Synechron Inc Weehawken, NJ

- The project enables CMS to screen Medicare providers and suppliers using automated data checks and risk-assessment methods enabling it to proactively identify fraud, waste, and abuse.
- The APS (Automated Provider Screening) application verifies enrollment and re-enrollment data for all provider/suppliers and output results
  of data checks.
- Provides a screening results interface to pass results of enrollment data and risk screening back to CMS and CMS business partners.
- This software supports new/updated sources of data to improve the accuracy of data checks/risk identification.
- The verification and screening methods is comprehensive, covering all Medicare provider/supplier categories and types, to include physicians and non-physician practitioners, and encompassing providers in all 50 states and 6 territories.
- APS uses data from CMS and other sources to support a risk scoring engine for automated screening of Medicare FFS program providers.
- The project was based on Agile methodology and new requirements and changes were made, application deployed and product version releases, maintenance and performance patch releases were sent to the customer.
- Responsibilities: Was with the Scoring engine team where rules were designed in java to match Pecos data with APS data Used JPA to
  persist data into database and Hibernate Developed reusable and extensible JUnit test cases on modules during the development phase, to
  test whether the code is functioning properly Kettle Pentaho is the ETL tool used to extract PECOS file, listing new providers and
  reassigned cases.
- Did Pre Pre-Validation to ensure validation of the field level input for data quality, format, and length.
- Used SQL as an open source database and performed some SQL queries for the retrieval of information Involved in Extraction,
   Transformation and Loading of data where I performed some transformations to convert csv, text and xml files into tables using Pentaho
   Performed detailed analysis on data loaded from source Implemented some validations to ascertain that required information is loaded in the
   database Prepared technical design documentation and explanatory material Deployed the application using Apache Tomcat Developed
   presentation layer using JSP, HTML, JavaScript Developed Restful web services to update the feeds using JAX-RS(Apache CXF) Tested
   the above Restful Web services using SOAP UI tool.
- Involve and cross collaborate with teams to discuss on the new implementation and any issues in the product to be resolved Involved in
  fixing bugs in the product and write unit test-cases using JUnit Analyzed the existing architecture and prepared new architecture which
  supports new proposed technologies and existing functionality Responsible for integration work, lead the integration team Ensured timely
  deliveries of work requests/enhancements by coordinating the team Involved coding using JAVA, JEE, XML and JavaScript.
- Unit testing and review of the system.
- Environment: J2EE, Hibernate3.0, JPA, JSP, Kettle Pentaho 4.2.0, XML, JUNIT, ANT, Apache, SQL, PL/SQL, Linux, Windows, Java, JEE, Multi-Threading, Collections, Exception Handling, RESTful WebServices, Eclipse, Spring, Struts, Hibernate, CXF, Servlets, Java, JSP, EJB, SOAPUI, Jboss, Maven and Linux.

## **Education and Training**

Bachelor of Arts: Computer Science Economics Middlebury College City, State, USA Computer Science Economics Strills

Java, C+++, C#, SQL. Mobile technology: Android. SDK's and plugins: Android SDK and Android ADT. IDE: Eclipse, Net beans. Simulators: Google Android Simulator. Web Technologies: XML, HTML5, JSON, XML Parser, REST, and JSP. Servers: Oracle-WLS, Apache Tomcat 6.0, HTTP. Databases: SQLite, MySQL. Frameworks: Android, J2EE. Editors: Notepad, Notepad+++, Sublime Text. Operating Systems: Linux, Windows 7, 8.